A Finding Aid to the Dean Cornwell papers, circa 1893-1981, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Dean Cornwell papers
1893-1981
Archives of American Art
Cornwell, Dean, 1892-1960
AAA.corndean
Archival Resource Key
3.9 Linear feet
The papers of Dean Cornwell measure 3.9 linear feet and date from circa 1893-1981. They illustrate his career through biographical material, correspondence, writings, printed and photographic material, and artwork.
Biographical / Historical
Dean Cornwell (1892-1960) was a muralist, painter, and illustrator who worked primarily in New York.
Cornwell was born in Louisville, Kentucky. He began his career as a cartoonist for the Louisville Herald and then moved to Chicago where he studied at the Art Institute and worked for the Chicago Tribune. In 1915 he moved to New Rochelle, New York where he studied under Harvey Dunn at the Art Students League of New York. Eventually he traveled to London where he began to study mural painting under Frank Brangwyn.
Cornwell was a teacher at the Art Students League in New York, served as President of the Society of Illustrators (1922-1926), and was elected to its Hall of Fame in 1959. In 1934, he was elected Associate Academician into the National Academy of Design, and became a full Academician in 1940. He also served as president of the National Society of Mural painters from 1953 to 1957. At the peak of his career, he earned the nickname "Dean of Illustrators".
Cornwell's artwork was featured in multiple publications including Cosmopolitan, Harper's Bazaar, Redbook, and Good Housekeeping. He painted many murals during his career including those found in the Sir Walter Raleigh Room in the Hotel Warwick, the Lincoln Memorial Shrine in Redlands, and the General Motors Mural at the 1939 World's Fair in New York.
Cornwell died on December 4th, 1960 at the age of sixty-eight in New York City.
Arrangement
This collecton contains six series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1930-1961 (.1 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1933-1981 (.2 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1930-1978 (.7 Linear feet: Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, circa 1924-1970 (1.1 Linear feet: Box 2, OV 5, and OV 6)
Series 5: Photographic Material, circa 1893-1960 (1.7 Linear feet: Boxes 2-4, OV 7, and OV 8)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1934 (.1 Linear feet: Box 3)
Scope and Contents
The Dean Cornwell papers measure 3.9 linear feet and date from circa 1893-1981. Biographical material consists of a resume, obituaries for Cornwell, estate papers referencing various inheritances, multiple membership and award certificates, and material relating to a Who's Who in America article featuring Cornwell. Correspondence is to and from Dean Cornwell and is with artists and business associates. Writings include various essays by Cornwell as well as multiple diaries. Also included are the transcript of a biography about Cornwell titled Dean Cornwell: Dean of Illustrators (1978) by Patricia Janus Broder and two article drafts. Printed material consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs, printed reproductions of Cornwell's artwork, news clippings, and two scrapbooks of artwork by others. Photographic material includes personal photographs and photographs of Cornwell as well as photographs of his mural projects. Also included are a set of fifty-seven glass plate negatives which depict various drawings by Cornwell. Artwork includes a folder of sketches.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Papers were donated in 1984 by Lucy Cornwell, daughter of Dean Cornwell.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reels 3781-3783 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Mural painting and decoration, American; Mural painting and decoration -- 20th century -- United States; Scrapbooks; Illustrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State); Muralists -- New York (State) -- New York; Broder, Patricia Janis
- Biographical Material, circa 1930-1961; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material consists of a resume, obituaries for Cornwell, estate papers, multiple membership and award certificates, and material relating to a Who's Who in America article featuring Cornwell.
  - Resume, circa 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituaries, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Estate Papers, circa 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The American Legion 193rd Convention Corporation of New York City, Certificate, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Architectural league of New York, Certificate, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Confederate Air Corps, Parody Certificate, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Academy of Design, Certificate, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - National Society of Mural Painters, Membership List, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Society of Illustrators, Certificate, circa 1930-1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Who's Who In America, Biographical Information, circa 1955-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - George Washington University Club Reception Button, circa 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Wedding Invitiation, Patricia and Dean Bedford, circa 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Address Book, circa 1941-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, circa 1958-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, circa 1933-1981; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; .2 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is to and from Dean Cornwell and is with artists and business associates.
  - Correspondence (1930s), circa 1933-1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence (1940s), circa 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (1950s), circa 1950-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Correspondence (1960s), circa 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence (1980s), circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1933-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Writings, circa 1930-1978; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; .7 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings include various titled essays by Cornwell, as well as multiple diaries. Also included are the transcript of a biography titled Dean Cornwell: Dean of Illustrators (1978) by Patricia Janus Broder and two drafts of articles about Cornwell.
  - By Cornwell, Archival Resource Key
    - "Art", circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "The Gomper's Room", circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "New York World's Fair Mural", circa 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Religion", circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Sir Walter Raleigh Room", circa 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Symbolism, Story of Angels, Ideas for Mural Subjects", circa 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Diary, circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Diary, circa 1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Diary, circa 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Diary, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Diary, circa 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - By Others, Archival Resource Key
    - Dean Cornwell: Dean of Illustrators (1978) by Patricia Janus Broder, Manuscript, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Dean Cornwell", Ebell Magazine, circa 1931; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Dean Cornwell" by Willis Birchman, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, circa 1924-1970; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 2, OV 5, and OV 6
  Printed material consists of exhibition announcements and catalogs, printed reproductions of Cornwell's artwork including magazine serial illustrations and christmas cards, news clippings, and two scrapbooks of artwork by others.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1953-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1941-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Christmas Cards Illustrated by Cornwell, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Color Reproductions from Magazines, circa 1930-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - D.T.C. Event Book, circa 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Illustrations of Dean Cornwell, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Magazine Serial Illustrations, circa 1924-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Magazine Illustrations by Other Artists, Scrapbook, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Magazine Serial Illustrations, circa 1924-1925; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Magazines, circa 1940-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
  - News Clippings, circa 1926-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - News Clippings, circa 1926-1963; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
  - Pictures of Works by Harvey Dunn, Scrapbook, circa 1940-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Published Articles about Cornwell, circa 1940-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Publications Featuring Artwork, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
- Photographic Material, circa 1893-1960; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-4, OV 7, and OV 8
  Photographic material includes photographs of Cornwell, family, and friends. Also included are photographs of his mural projects and photographic prints of a set of fifty-seven glass plate negatives which include a set of nitrate negatives stored separately.
  - Cornwell, Dean, circa 1920-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Cornwell, Dean, circa 1920-1960; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Dean Cornwell and Family, circa 1893-1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Dean Cornwell with Professional Friends, circa 1925-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dean Cornwell with Professional Friends, Negatives, circa 1925-1953; Archival Resource Key; Folder three contains negatives with vinegar syndrome. (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Cornwell's Trip to India, circa 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cornwell's Trip to India, Negatives, circa 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cornwell's Models, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Cornwell's Models, Negatives, circa 1930-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mural Projects, Archival Resource Key
    - American Battle Monument Projects, circa 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Davidson County Courthouse, Nashville, Tennessee, circa 1937; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Detroit Athletic Club: Men's Bar, circa 1936; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Eastern Airline, circa 1946; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - The Lincoln Shrine, circa 1927-1932; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Los Angeles Public Library, circa 1927-1933; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - National Bank, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - New England Telephone Company, circa 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Pioneers of American Medicine", Series, circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Sir Walter Raleigh Room, circa 1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Strength and Safety", General Motors Building at the New York's World Fair, circa 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tennessee State Building, circa 1941; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified Mural, circa 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous Projects, circa 1925-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Painting, Drawings, and Cartoons for Murals (1935), Exhibition, circa 1935; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Biblical Paintings, circa 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Biblical Paintings, Negatives, circa 1940-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Magazine Artwork, Color Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mural Artwork, Color Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29-35)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Slides, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Photographs of Artwork, Glass Plate Prints, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 37-40)
  - Photographs of Art Work, Glass Plate Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 4)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR1)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR2)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR4)
  - Nitrate Negatives, circa 1920-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box NTR8)
- Artwork, circa 1934; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; .1 Linear feet Box 3
  Artwork includes a folder of sketches.
  - Sketches, circa 1934; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 41)